I see you as someone who has experience
with obviously whistleblowing and what's
going on with
our CIA and the military, but also a
real inside side view of what it's like
to be incarcerated in this country and
see from inside what the criminal
justice system is here.
And I can't help but see parallels
between when you talk about like torture
that we do to people across the globe, I
can't help but draw parallels to how we
treat our inmates that are incarcerated
in a lot of cases.
And so I was I was wondering if you
could talk about
examples of that you might have seen or
that you know of where our system here
in this country is what we would
consider to be acting immorally in how
we treat our incarcerated citizens.
>> [snorts]
>> We don't have time for that
conversation. I don't know.
Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> I'll give you a couple examples.
Um
Yeah.
>> But I'm right is that if there is a
parallel like it's the same thing. You
are 100% right. So listen, the United
Nations has declared
our use of solitary confinement to be a
form of torture.
Right? International standards are that
someone can't be held in solitary
confinement confinement for more than 14
days.
We have prisoners who have been in
solitary confinement and I mean
solitary.
No contact with another human being for
more than 40 years.
40 years.
You lose your mind after a couple of
months. Yeah, I think to me even when
you say 14 days, I think that you know,
to me two or three days would feel like
14 days if No, you're sleeping on a on a
steel slab with a small sink and a
toilet.
Uh your room is 6 by 10 ft and all you
can do is walk in circles. You know,
they say that you are allowed 1 hour of
exercise every day that it's 23 hours of
solitary. That's nonsense. What that 1
hour of exercise is that there's a steel
door at the back of your of your cell
and it leads out into a cage that's
another 6 by 10 ft.
And so you can walk in a little circle
outside for 1 hour.
And that's it. It's still solitary. So
you have people losing their minds
constantly. And don't forget that that
psychological studies that have been
published as recently as as a year and a
half ago
have found that 85%
of incarcerated Americans suffer from
some sort of mental illness. Most
commonly
antisocial personality disorder. So
you're already kind of on the edge.
Besides the fact that everybody in
prison is depressed, lots of people are
bipolar, some are schizophrenic. We used
to have this thing called zombie pill
line where, you know, if you need if you
need insulin, you get in line at 6:00
a.m. and 6:00 p.m. and they give you
your insulin. But if you're insane, you
get in line at 7:00 p.m. and you get
your pills that turn you into a zombie.
And so we called it zombie pill line.
There was a guy in solitary confinement
in my prison who had been in for so long
and was so desperate to get out that he
smashed the window
of the cell and ate the broken glass.
And then he called for help and he said,
"I ate broken glass." and they told him,
"Tough luck."
Well, the glass shredded his stomach and
he ended up bleeding to death.
And that kind of thing happens all the
time. I'll give you another example.
Um when I first got to prison, I went to
my case manager and I said, "Listen,
I've got a master's degree in Middle
Eastern studies, policy analysis. I I
did my PhD coursework in international
affairs. I'd be happy to teach a GED
class
uh if if you want me to. Can I swear on
this show?"
Absolutely.
And he looked at me and he said,
"Kiriakou, if I want you to teach a
[__] class, I'll ask you to teach a
[__] class." And they made me a
janitor in the chapel. That was my job.
I think a lot of this a lot of this also
goes to the privatization and the profit
motive.
Um It's far worse in private prisons.
This was a federal prison, so it
this was government, but you're right.
The private prisons are far worse
because of the profit motive. The only
way they can make a profit is to cut
back on food and on medicine. Remind me
of that. I'm going to come back to that
in a moment. So um
I was in the um
in the chapel
and every day I would walk past this one
guy's cell. He was an older Italian guy.
And I liked him. I liked all the
Italians.
So he was kind of doubled over one day
and I said, "Hey man, what's wrong?"
He said, "Man, my back is killing me.
Like really killing me. I can't sleep or
anything." and I said, "Oh, you should
go to the uh
you should go to the the medical unit."
He goes down there and they did what
they do for everybody no matter what
your complaint is. They gave him
Tylenol.
And then I saw him
I don't know, a couple weeks later and
he had a walker. And I said, "Is your
back that bad?" And he said, "I feel
like I'm paralyzed."
And he said, "Every time I go to
medical, they give me a they give me
Tylenol."
So
couple of more weeks pass and I see him
in a wheelchair.
So I went to the chaplain and I said,
"Chaplain, you've got to do something
about this. They're not paying any
attention to him at medical and
something is clearly wrong with him."
So the chaplain, to his credit, weighed
in. The chaplain was the only decent
human being I met
in in the entire system.
And um so he went and he said something
to medical and finally after like 6
weeks, medical took him out to a
hospital for an x-ray.
And he had stage four spinal cancer.
And he applied for a compassionate
release so that he could die at home.
The warden went to his cell
and told him that if he would sign a
paper saying that
that they treated him appropriately in
medical,
they would let him go.
Well, he knew he was
a dead man. He only had a couple of days
left and he wanted his wife and his
children to be able to sue the system
for killing him, which is what they did.
And he refused to sign and they wouldn't
let him go. He died in his bunk.
And and that's that's typical of what's
going on there. Yeah. I think and and a
lot of it is
racially motivated in our criminal
justice system from start to finish. I
mean,
most obviously we have higher amounts of
incarcerated people of color than
percentage of of people of color. So
it's very disproportionate and that's
something I think that I I see it every
level. Um is that something that you
experienced when you were inside?
Without a doubt. My my prison was
typical of the demographic breakdown in
the federal prison system. It was it was
roughly 50% black,
30% Hispanic and 20% white. And most of
the whites were pedophiles.
So that that was that was absolutely
typical of of the entire system. And how
long were you there? How how does
someone like you get on there? I mean,
clearly you're not a typical you're not
the typical inmate. Although with the
amount of whistleblowers that do get I
mean, you're you might start to have
more company in there, but
>> Right. Yeah. How does someone like you
you're a very nice, you're pretty, you
know, you're you're not you don't strike
me as a prison material. So how that's a
23 months is a long time. It's a long
time.
>> time. I said to one of the Italians
before I answer your question. We were
we were on a walk together and he was a
a senior
captain in the Bonanno crime family
and had been in prison
>> [laughter]
>> much of his adult life. So we're walking
around the track and he asked me how
much time I had and I said
I said, "2 years. Feels like 20 years."
And he said, "2 years, you could do that
standing on your head." and I said, "I
don't know, man. I don't know how I'm
going to get through this." I had only
been in about 6 weeks. And he said, "Let
me give you some advice.
If anybody asks you how much time you
have, you tell them 5 years because if
they hear that your sentence is so
short, they're going to kick your ass."
And so I began telling everybody that I
had 5 years and then when it came time
to leave, I was gone. What happens is
when people see on the checkout sheet
that you're leaving the next day,
a gang of people will come into your
cell and just beat the [__] out of you.
Just because they're jealous that it's
not them.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> But you asked me how I got into that
prison. There's a story there.
So when I agreed to take the plea and
was sentenced, my lawyers asked the
judge if she would send me to a minimum
security work camp.
Well, minimum security camps are always
across the street from a higher security
prison because when there's a riot, it's
the the campers who then go across the
street to the main prison and they do
the cooking and the laundry and the
sweeping and scrubbing the floors and
stuff like that.
So uh the judge asked the prosecutors,
"Any objection?" They said, "No, no
objection." Well, the thing about the
camp is there are there are no bars on
the windows, the doors are unlocked,
there are no fences, you're free to come
and go as you please. You're on your
honor not to abscond. And frankly, most
of the prisoners work in town at the
local college, you know, as janitors or
whatever.
>> So it's like a work release. Like you
get day time off.
>> Yeah. You sleep in the prison, but you
work outside.
>> Okay.
So, uh the prosecution had no objection,
and she said, you know, "So ordered."
So, I I go you pri- prison is the oddest
thing. You just drive up to the prison
and knock on the door and turn yourself
in.
So, that's what I did. I uh
documentary film crew, one of my
lawyers,
um and my cousin and his son all drove
me up there, and I went to the camp, and
they said, "You have to go across the
street to the main prison first and
check in, and then come back over here."
I said, "Okay." So, I went over to the
prison
and uh said, "I'm John Kiriakou. I'm
here to turn myself in."
And they put me through the metal
detector and frisked me, and then the
cop starts to lead me around to the back
of the prison.
And I said, "No, no. I said, I'm
supposed to be over here at the at the
camp."
And he laughed at me, and he said, "Not
according to my paperwork, you're not."
And I told myself, "Take it easy.
There's nothing you can do. If you raise
a fuss, they're going to put you in
solitary." So, I didn't say a word.
It took me 5 days before I got access to
a telephone, and I called my lawyer, one
of my 11 lawyers, the one who I liked
and trusted the most.
And I said, "Hey, they put me in the
actual prison with the the mafia dons
and the drug kingpins and the and the
perverts." I said, "What do I do?"
And he said, "Oh my gosh. Well, we could
file a motion, but it'll be 2 years
before we get a court hearing. You'll be
home by then." He said, "I'm sorry,
buddy. You're going to have to tough it
out."
And so, I decided, "You know what?
You're trained for this. You've lived in
far worse places than this, far more
dangerous places than this." I said,
"I'm going to fall back on my CIA
training, and I'm going to make sure
that I remain at the top of the heap." I
actually wrote a book about it that won
one of the country's most prestigious
literary awards. It's called Doing Time
Like a Spy: How the CIA Taught Me to
Survive and Thrive in Prison. And I use
these these 20 life lessons that the CIA
taught us in training
um to make sure that I was safe, and I
was at the top of the social heap, and
nobody messed with me. And I'll tell
you, in 23 months, nobody messed with
me.
So, getting out when you come out of
there, I mean, now you have, obviously,
a felony on your record, which is a big
deal, um especially for someone who's
coming from an academic and professional
background. That's not the kind of thing
that you normally would have to deal
with. So, where do you Where do What do
you do with that? Oof, that's a really
great question, and it it it was a very
difficult thing. You know, people don't
realize that when you have a felony,
there's no such thing as having paid
your debt to society. You're always a
felon.
You you can't vote. You can't hold a
professional license. Like, how that has
anything to do with professional
licenses, I have no idea. You can't ever
own a gun again.
>> I don't know what it has to do with
voting, to be honest. I've never
understood the connection.
I Nor nor did I. Although, I had I had
kind of a good experience with that. I
can tell you about it in a minute. But,
um you get out. They put me They They
didn't put me in, but they assigned me
to a halfway house. I
I so angered the the warden by writing a
blog and smuggling it out of prison that
that I didn't get any halfway house
time, not a single day. I had to do my
entire sentence.
Not a single day off. So, they assigned
me to this halfway house called Hope
Village, which has since been closed. We
used to call it either Hopeless Village
or Abandon All Hope Village. 140 men,
they had one job posted on the job
board, and it was to work at a car wash.
For 140 men. So, you get out, and they
say, "You have 90 days to find a job,
and if you can't, you go back in."
Back in for the next 7 months. And you
can't find a job, because how can you
possibly find a job?
>> You're a felon. How are you going to
find a job? So, I was lucky. I was
luckier than the other 139 guys in
there, because I was kind of famous.
And so,
I had a a think tank, a progressive
think tank that reached out to me and
said, "Um we can't pay you much. We can
only pay you minimum wage, but
it's a job." So, I took that, and then
after 6 months, I had to raise the money
for my own salary. So, I was doing like
GoFundMe and all this silly stuff just
to make minimum wage. Well, minimum wage
didn't put food on my table, you know?
And so, I sort of bounced around from
job to job. I ended up getting a job as
a radio host, which was a good fit for
me and gave me the best health insurance
I ever had in my life,
but it wasn't enough money to really
make a living.
And then finally, my wife said, "Screw
this. I'm out of here." And she took
off.
So, you know, I I Here I am. I'm I'm in
my mid-50s, and I I had to start all
over again. What really saved me, and
this is unique to me. This is not I'm
far luckier than than any other felon.
>> Far luckier. Is that I am a I'm a
national hero in Greece. When I When I
first got in trouble, the Greek uh
ambassador
approached me, and he said, "What can we
do to be helpful?" And I said, "You
could give me Greek citizenship."
And he did.
So,
>> okay.
>> Here I'm this guy this, you know,
this The Greeks are fascinated by the
CIA. They always have been. So, here's
this Greek-American CIA guy who made
good and blew the whistle and took it on
the chin, cuz he wanted to do the right
thing and tell the truth. And so, um
the Greek government hired me to write a
new whistleblower protection law for
them.
So, I went to Greece five times in 2015.
We came up with the whistleblower
protection law,
and we presented it to the European
Parliament in Brussels. So, I testified
twice in Brussels before the Parliament,
and they passed it into law, and then
the Greek Parliament passed it into law,
and now it's the law of the land for the
entire European Union. Well, this was
covered in the news in Greece. Oh,
here's John Kiriakou again. I'll tell
you a funny story. I arrived I arrived
at the airport,
and I hadn't shaven, and my hair was
like this, cuz I was flying coach, and I
get off, and I come out of the doors
from customs,
and there all these camera crews with
their cameras, right? And I turn to look
to see, "Oh, there must be somebody
famous on my plane."
>> [laughter]
>> And then they run up to me.
And I I actually started to laugh. Like
you were like, "What is this?" Yeah,
yeah, I looked terrible, and why would
you
>> [laughter]
>> want to talk to me? Well, they wanted to
talk about this whistleblower protection
law, because there was a big scandal. A
whistleblower blew the whistle on the
Minister of Defense. He had taken bribes
from Siemens, and and it was the first
time that the law was actually being
used in court. So, um after that,
I I got so much press coverage from that
that a consortium of Greece's four
wealthiest families um put together a
a private equity fund, like a hedge
fund, and they asked me to run it.
And so, I've been doing that since
August, and I finally like made it in
life, and uh you know, made my big
comeback. But, I'm still a convicted
felon here. Yeah. You know, I still get
hassled
>> Greek.
It's a good thing you're Greek, huh?
It's a good thing I'm Greek, because if
I wasn't Greek, I'd still be making
minimum wage someplace.
Right. So, the Greeks they saved you.
Yeah, they did. They saved me.
>> [music]